Today's דף daf is
מ"ו mem vav and we pick up at the bottom of מ"ה
עמוד ב mem hay amud bet and as we saw yesterday the
major part of the discussion is what types of things might רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon agree to are problem of מוקצה muktza and whether
we rule like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So yesterday we mentioned that
רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon's concern with cases he would agree would first
of all be the burning lamp, which is an issue of הוקצה
למצותו, huksa l'mitzvaso, maybe not related at all to the מוקצה לשבת
ויום טוב. muktza l'shabbos v'yomtov.
Then he would agree to the cases of the raisins, which is
something that you pushed away and is אינו ראוי, aino raoy, but
then he starts agreeing to other cases as well. Animals on יום
טוב Yom Tov that are normally out of the house or perhaps
newly born, a newly born chick and so on. Now the גמרא
Gemara continues with the following. אמר
ליה אביי לרב יוסף. amlei Abaye l'Rav Yosef. The line starts with
the word יוסף Yosef and it's about ten lines before the lines
get wide, maybe eight lines before the lines get wide. It says
יוסף Yosef about twelve lines from the bottom. The גמרא Gemara says
like this: אמר
ליה אביי לרב יוסף. amlei Abaye l'Rav Yosef. So אביי Abaye said
to רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, ואת לא תסבר דרבי יוחנן כרבי יהודה
סבירא ליה? v'at lo tisbor d'Rabbi Yochanan k'Rabbi Yehuda s'vira lei?
So the whole question was whether רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan's position was
like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda because רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was reported
as saying that they say the הלכה halacha is like רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon and the גמרא Gemara said yesterday, concluded yesterday based on
other reports,
that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan himself does not hold like רבי שמעון,
Rabbi Shimon, holds like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and they means other
say. אביי Abaye now challenges רב יוסף Rav Yosef and says, ואת
לא תסבר דרבי יוחנן כרבי יהודה סבירא ליה? v'at lo tisbor d'Rabbi
Yochanan k'Rabbi Yehuda s'vira lei? Don't you also agree that רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan holds like רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? והא רב אבא ורב
אסי
איקלעו לבי רבי אבא דמן חיפה? v'ha Rav Abba v'Rav Assi ikla
l'vei Rabbi Abba d'min Cheifa? But don't
we know that רב אבא Rav Abba and רב אסי Rav Assi
came to the house of רבי אבא Rabbi Abba from חיפה, Cheifa,
not I don't know if he means Haifa, Cheifa, ונפל מנורתא על
גלימא דרב אסי, v'nafal m'norta al glima d'Rav Assi,
and a candelabrum, some type of I guess standing candelabrum, fell on
the coat of רב אסי Rav Assi and presumably this was שבת.
Shabbos. ולא טלטלה v'lo tiltelah
and he refused to move it. So look here, presumably this was
something that it was burning when שבת Shabbos began, was now burnt
out. I hope it wasn't burning when it fell on his coat.
Okay, that's a different story we're going to get to in a
later פרק perek about what happens if you've got a fire and
how do you put it out and protect yourself even though it's
שבת. Shabbos. Anyway, it had been burning when שבת Shabbos began, now
it fell on his coat
and he didn't move it. Now if you remember in the משנה,
Mishna, that was the position of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
or of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that even after it burns out
it's a problem, but it was not the position of רבי שמעון.
Rabbi Shimon. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says after it's burnt out it's
no problem. So מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, why did he refuse to
move it? לאו משום דרב אסי תלמידה דרבי יוחנן הוה? lav mishum
d'Rav Assi talmida d'Rabbi Yochanan hava? It must be, thank you so
much, it must be that רב אסי Rav Assi number one is
a student of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, ורבי יוחנן כרבי יהודה סבירא
ליה v'Rabbi Yochanan k'Rabbi Yehuda s'vira lei and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
holds like רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? So you see he didn't move
it even after it burns out, that's not a רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon position, that's a clear רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda position and he's
a student of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, so from this we can
infer that רבי אבא Rabbi Abba hold that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
holds like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and not like רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon. אמר ליה amlei he said back to him כרבי יהודה סבירא
ליה דאית ליה מוקצה k'Rabbi Yehuda s'vira lei d'is lei muktza he
holds like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that he holds of מוקצה muktza
that's why he didn't move this מנורה. m'nora. אמר ליה amlei he
said back to him מנורתא קאמרת? m'norta ka'amart? You're talking about a
מנורה? m'nora? מנורתא שאני, m'norta shani, מנורה m'nora is different. Again, this
does not mean a חנוכה מנורה, Chanukah m'nora, it means you know
some type of a standing candelabrum. דאמר ריש לקיש בצידן, d'amar Reish
Lakish b'Tzidan, as ריש לקיש Reish Lakish ruled in צידן, Tzidan, מנורתא
הניטלת בידו אחת מותר לטלטלה. m'norta haniteles b'yado achas mutar l'taltela.
If you have a type of a candelabrum that's held in one
hand, then you're allowed to carry it. You know like when they
ever have like in those vampire movies, you know going down with
the candelabrum. So if you have the candelabrum that's held in one
hand, you're allowed to move it on שבת, Shabbos, again not while
it's burning.
בשתי ידיו b'shtei yado in something that requires two hands, like it's
a huge floor one, not a hand one, so then אסור לטלטלה
ossur l'taltela you can't move it. ורבי יוחנן אמר v'Rabbi Yochanan amar
and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says אנו אין לנו anu ein lanu
the only permission that we have to move these types of lamps
or whatever is אלא בנר כרבי שמעון. ela b'ner k'Rabbi Shimon. When
you're dealing not with say a מנורה m'nora but when you're dealing
with a lamp, then we would rule like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
that after it blows out you're allowed to move it.
אבל מנורתא aval m'norta but when it comes to a מנורה m'nora
בין בידו אחת בין בשתי ידיו אסור לטלטלה bein b'yado achas bein
b'shtei yado ossur l'taltela whether it's one hand or two hands you
can't. Now this we have to explain because here it says that
he basically seems to rule like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that after
a lamp blows out you can move it, so it's not a
concern of מוקצה muktza and nevertheless for some reason by this candelabrum
he's got a problem, so there seems to be some special problem
with the candelabrum. So
מאי טעמא mai ta'ama what's the reason for this? ואמר
רבה ורב יוסף דאמרי תרוייהו v'amar Rabba v'Rav Yosef d'amrei tarvaihu so
רבה Rabba and רב יוסף Rav Yosef both say הואיל ואדם קובע
לו מקום ho'il v'adam koveia lo makom
because a מנורה m'nora is different, a מנורה m'nora is something... is
a type of a thing that you designate a place and you
don't plan on moving, so it's again one of these categories of
like a hands-off type of a thing. Okay, so something this candelabra
you don't move your candelabra all around the house, although it's funny
you would think that a single hand one you would, it's made
for walking, but maybe he makes a type of a low plug
but at least a floor-based one you designate a place for it
and you don't move it. And that's a type of a situation
that maybe even רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon could agree to. So just
because you heard that a student of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan didn't
move a מנורה, menorah, doesn't prove that he holds like רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, he holds against רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. מנורה Menorah is
special, you designate a place, leave, you hands-off, you don't touch it,
and therefore even perhaps רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon might agree to that.
So now the גמרא Gemara is going to see if that's the
reason behind the מנורה. menorah. Let's take a look. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this: אמר ליה אביי לרב יוסף, Amar lei Abaye
le'Rav Yosef, so אביי Abaye said to רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, והרי
כילת חתנים, ve'harei kilat chatanim, what about a type of a canopy
bed? דאדם קובע לו מקום, de'adam kove'a lo makom, nobody ever, you
know, you don't move around the canopy of a bed, you got
your bed with the canopy spread above it, and nobody fools with
the canopy on a regular basis. ואמר שמואל משום רבי חייא, Ve'amar
Shmuel mishum Rabbi Chiya, and nevertheless שמואל Shmuel says in the name
of רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, כילת חתנים מותר לנטותה ומותר לפרקה בשבת,
kilat chatanim mutar lintota u'mutar leparka be'Shabbat,
that you can both spread the canopy and take it down on
שבת. Shabbat. Now why is this? Normally, as we discussed yesterday by
a hut, you cannot erect or
deconstruct an אוהל ohel on שבת, Shabbat, an אוהל ohel meaning like
a flat surface that's a טפח tefach by a טפח tefach off
the ground and whatever made to protect things underneath it, meaning when
we get to this discussion we'll see that you know I sort
of mentioned it already by the case of the dead body that
sometimes they allowed it when it was done in an unusual way,
also sometimes they allow it if it's really not done to protect
things underneath it. Like why can you open up a folding table
on שבת? Shabbat? You're making an אוהל ohel for the space underneath
it. Why can you open a folding chair on שבת? Shabbat? So
anyway, so obviously there are exceptions to this rule. But if it's
made for the space underneath it and it's spread on שבת, Shabbat,
that's forbidden. But he says by a canopy bed you're allowed. Why?
Because a canopy bed, the one specifically referred to as a כילת
חתנים, kilat chatanim, like a bride's room bed, that was actually done
like a teepee. It wasn't flat, it was a teepee, it came
to a point at the top and then it spread down. So
that's not an אוהל. ohel. An אוהל ohel is something that only
has a טפח, tefach, right, like about three, four inches width at
the top, but something that comes to a point is not. So
therefore he said you could actually spread the canopy and remove the
canopy on שבת. Shabbat. Now that's very nice for the laws of
אוהל, ohel, but if once you have the canopy spread you leave
it there, right, it's not something that you take down every week
to wash or whatever, you leave it there for I don't know
years or months or whatever, then why can you take it down
on שבת? Shabbat? Why don't we say it's מוקצה? muktzah? It's something
that is קובע מקום, kove'a makom, you set it in a place
and you don't move it. So you see that that cannot be
the reason. Now תוספות Tosafot says there actually is a category of
things you're קובע מקום kove'a makom that is מוקצה. muktzah. The argument
of the גמרא Gemara is that not that the category doesn't exist,
but that this is not a significant enough sort of example of
that to fall in that category. I think something we normally would
call this like מוקצה מחמת חסרון כיס, muktzah machmat chisaron kis, you
know, but like this is a good example of this concept, although
the way we categorize it is differently. I have my precious, you
know, Ming vase on the mantel, don't touch it. You're visiting my
house, don't move that, we don't move that, right? So that's like
קובע לו מקום kove'a lo makom that you don't want anybody moving
it. But not something like a floor lamp that every now and
then I might need to move around for some type of a
reason and it's not to the same degree of hands-off. So that
cannot be the reason that a מנורה menorah is special, that would
not be so much in that hands-off category even if conceptually this
category of קובע מקום kove'a makom exists, this would not fall into
it. Yes, Joel?
Are we going to talk about אוהלים ohalim more?
Absolutely. Okay, I have a bunch of questions.
All right, yes.
A lot of things we do in passing, but you know but
we can't unpack all of them at once. אוהל Ohel will have
its own focused discussion. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues like
this: אלא אמר אביי, Ella amar Abaye, so what's special about this
מנורה menorah that we said, you know, hands-off, even if we might
normally rule like רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? We said you don't move
a מנורה. menorah. So אלא אמר אביי בשל חוליות עסקינן, ella amar
Abaye be'shel chulyot askinan,
we're talking about a one of of sections, and apparently they would
have a מנורה menorah that you would actually like screw in the
various parts, okay, and you could maybe also,
I think there are some things like this that I've seen, that
anyway, you know, how many arms you would have, you could change
at different times, right, because you could always screw in an additional
arm into additional hole, so you could have like a many-armed candelabrum,
or you need less light so you unscrew some of the arms.
So why is that an issue? That's an issue because you can't
screw in those arms on שבת. Shabbat. What we're now going to
touch on a little bit today is the discussion of בניין, binyan,
or of if not בניין binyan because we rule אין בניין בכלים,
ein binyan be'keilim, building is something that we don't say applies to
vessels, but what we do say applies to the vessels is מכה
בפטיש. Makeh B'Patish. So it's exactly a question: who cares if you
call it בנין Binyan or מכה בפטיש? Makeh B'Patish? Either way, you're
not allowed to construct something with a vessel. Okay, so that's a
question, but either way, to create some type of a strong of
of either permanent construction or something that's construction-like in terms of the
process, like screwing something in, that is a problem on שבת. Shabbat.
So therefore we do not want you carrying a מנורה menorah because
even if you're not building it, you're just carrying it, it will
look like, you know, you might come to fix it if it
falls apart, or it'll look like you put it together. So it's
a type of a גזירה gezeirah because this is a type of
an object we don't because it's common that people might be adjusting
on שבת Shabbat and we don't want them doing that. Now of
course, as we'll see again as I said later, you know, tomorrow
as well, there are types of things that you do, you know,
sort of, you know, somewhat expand or contract on שבת Shabbat which
are allowed, like we're talking about a table, adding a leaf to
a table, certainly folding, but even something that's more like not just
the natural hinges. Adding a leaf to a table is something you're
allowed to do on שבת. Shabbat. Okay, so what makes this, you
know, where exactly to draw the line is something we'll see more
tomorrow. One issue certainly is the question about how tightly it's fit
together or not, how much it gets, it's about screwing and banging,
or it's not about that, it's just inserting and so on. Okay,
but that's what is special about this. So
let's take a look what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this. אי הכי מאי טעמא דרבי שמעון לקמן
דשרי? Ei hachi mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Shimon l'kaman d'sharei? So first גמרא
Gemara thinks what you actually did was that actually it fell down,
you know, as the question was is about is about whether you
can maybe actually move it, put it back up, and maybe even
construct it. But the גמרא Gemara says that's not possible. So what's
the reason of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon לקמן l'kaman that says that
it's okay? So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
that a single arm is okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: כעין חוליות. K'ein chulyot. No, we're not talking that actually like
it require like, you know, it has the it has the screw
the screw-in part. But it looks like it does. דאית ביה חדקי,
D'it bei chidkei, there are like there are like it's like engraved
circles on the arms. So if you look at it, it looks
like those engraving, you know, engraving the engravings all around it, it
looks like it was one of those things that was screwed in.
It's really not. It's really one piece. But it but it yeah,
it's like a מראית עין marit ayin problem. So let's take a
look, let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. הלכך, Hilkach, therefore, חוליות,
chulyot,
if it's got actual the act, you know, actually it's made of
pieces, בין גדולות בין קטנות אסור
לטלטלה. bein gedolot bein ktanot assur l'taltela. So whether it's big or
small, you cannot move it. Okay, why is that? So again, the
גמרא Gemara doesn't spell it out, but if you look at רש״י,
Rashi, like the fourth narrow line, רש״י Rashi says, גדולה הוי דרכה
לעשותה של חוליות. gedola hovei darcha la'asota shel chulyot.
I'm sorry, he's already going to the next answer of the גמרא.
Gemara.
So okay, let's keep on reading then. It says like this.
Right, I'm sorry, the first, let's look at the רש״י, Rashi, let's
look at רש״י Rashi at the first narrow line. He says, what's
the problem of one that really does have pieces? של פרקים, Shel
prakim, says רש״י, Rashi, שמא תיפול ותתפרק ויחזירנה ונמצא עושה כלי. shema
tipol v'titparek v'yachzirena v'nimtza oseh keli. So even
moving one that was actually like, you know, a complete a piece
that you have to screw together, even that, there really is no
problem carrying it. You're not screwing it together, you're just carrying it.
Ah, no, but it was so common that that type of thing
would need to be rescrewed or that you would rescrew it that
we said that was off limits. Okay, so it's quite interesting, like
what types of things are חז״ל, Chazal, you know, are they very
strict about that they feel is a very common concern, what types
of things are they not so strict about? It's really case-by-case. But
in this case, they've decided that this type of a מנורה menorah
is so common that it either needs adjusting or that people do
add components, they don't want you handling it at all on שבת,
Shabbat, if it genuinely is of these component parts. So that's if
it actually is of these component parts. Now now
that's whether big or small. גדולה, Gedola, a big one, נמי דאית
בה חדקי nami d'it bah chidkei that has these sort of engraved,
you know, markings on it, גזירה אטו גדולה דחוליות. gezeirah atu gedola
d'chulyot. Then everybody agrees don't do a big one because that will
lead to one that actually is of component pieces and there's a
bigger concern that the big one, you know, because the big one's
more normally, if you imagine, right, if you're going to make one
of little component pieces, it's probably going to be one of those
big ones, right? And then you, you know, it's a major type
of a thing and you're going to add various arms. A little
handheld one is probably just going to be more compact in general
and not one that you're going to so much be, you know,
having these different pieces. So the biggest concern was a big one
of various component pieces. So if it really is of component pieces,
חוליות, chulyot, it's a problem big or small, you'll come to fix
it. If it's not really of those pieces, it just looks like
it because it's got these markings, then we're going to say the
big one is off limits, that looks too much like the major
problematic case. כי פליגי, Ki pligi, when did they argue? בקטנה, B'ktana,
the small one, דאית בה חדקי d'it bah chidkei and it has
these markings. So it's like two degrees removed from the major concern.
The major concern is the big one with the component pieces. מר
סבר גזרינן, Mar savar gazrinan, one says nevertheless even that we say
don't don't move it, off limits. ומר סבר לא גזרינן. U'mar savar
lo gazrinan. That's how we ending. something that we make it when
we think it's a big concern and the other says we don't
make that גזירה. gezeira. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara has proven that
even a position that normally would only have a problem with a
lamp while it's burning like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon might have a
problem by מנורה Menorah for a special rabbinic concern. We don't want
you handling them, big or small, certainly when they're of component pieces,
maybe even if it's just markings, because these were the types of
things that would be very common to adjust on שבת Shabbat and
maybe also it's very common because you want an extra, you know,
arm of your candelabra and you screw in an extra arm, and
that was a concern about מכה בפטיש makeh bepatish or about building,
and therefore they said total hands off. Okay, so now we still
don't know what—now there's the issue about what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
said, because yesterday we ended with רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan saying,
with
the גמרא Gemara saying that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan rules like רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, and he just said people say like רבי שמעון,
Rabbi Shimon, but here he actually said
that we, you know, אין לנו אלא בנר כרבי שמעון, ein lanu
ela bener kerabbi shimon, we only hold by the נר ner like
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, so that sounds like we do hold by
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon by the נר. ner. Okay,
so רש״י Rashi says, yeah, that's all that proves is he says
that he's not concerned when the candle blows out, that it's like
the lamp is disgusting, it's מאוס. maos. So there he's ruling like
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, that after it goes out it's okay, but
he didn't say across the board we rule like רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon. So we still have this open question what רבי יוחנן's Rabbi
Yochanan position is. It's funny, it's rare that you have a גמרא
Gemara that spends so much time trying to figure out, like, what
did the תנאים Tannaim and אמוראים, Amoraim, you know, what do the
אמוראים Amoraim hold of these תנאים? Tannaim? Usually it's a little discussion
and then we decide הלכה כ Halacha ke X, but here we're
going on for like two pages trying to figure it out, so
it really seems like there was a very live question about whether
can we rely on רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and significantly limit מוקצה
muktzeh on שבת. Shabbat. Okay, so we had one version that רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said people said the ruling is like רבי שמעון,
Rabbi Shimon, we had another version that said רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
himself says it's like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, then we had רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan saying that we rule like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
by the lamp, but that might not mean we rule like רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon across the board, maybe it means only by the
lamp case, so we don't know. So now the גמרא Gemara continues,
let's take a look. ומי אמר רבי יוחנן הכי, umi amar rabbi
yochanan hachi, did רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan really say this? והאמר רבי
יוחנן הלכה כסתם משנה, veha'amar rabbi yochanan halacha kestam mishna, so we
normally, we know we have a general principle that רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan says the ruling is like a סתם משנה. stam mishna. ודתנן,
vedetnan, and we taught in the משנה: mishna: מוכני שלה, mukhni shela,
remember that fun case we had about three days ago about that
major debate of ראשונים Rishonim what the sort of thing it was
describing? I'll take it one way of תוספות, Tosafot, he says it
was talking about like a type of a dresser, and it has
a base. So if בזמן שהיא נשמטת, bizman shehi nishmetet, when the
base is removable from the
dresser—not a cabinet, dresser, I'm sorry, like a dresser, a cabinet is
a thing attached—if it's like a dresser and it has a base,
some type of a box that you store things in, a dresser
with a base, so if that base is removable, אין חיבור לה,
ein chibur la, it's not considered one unit with it for טומאה.
tuma. If you touch the base, it's not like you touched the
dresser and vice versa. ואין נמדדת עמה, ve'ein nimdedet ima, when you
measure it to say is it a big enough dresser that it
cannot be מקבל טומאה, mekabel tuma, because once something is a large
enough size it's not of a wood vessel, it cannot become מקבל
טומאה, mekabel tuma, you don't count the base together with the dresser
itself because it's detachable. ואין מצלת עמה באהל המת, ve'ein matzelet ima
be'ohel hamet, if it's all together and there's vessels in this dresser
and the dresser has a tight seal on it, then the vessels
in the dresser are not טמא tamei even if there's a dead
body in the room, but if there's an opening in the dresser
and the opening is being—this is what תוספות Tosafot reads it—partially closed
by the base, the base does not considered to seal off that
opening since it's detachable, and therefore the טומאה tuma would get into
the dresser through that opening. That's how תוספות Tosafot reads it. So
far, by the way, completely not relevant to us, this is a
משנה mishna in כלים, Keilim, which is why it has all these
טומאה tuma and טהרה taharah concerns. Be thankful that there's no בבלי
Bavli on כלים, Keilim, all right? This is just one example, every
משנה mishna is like this in כלים, Keilim, I gotta tell you.
Okay, and anyway, ואין מצלת עמה באהל המת, ve'ein matzelet ima be'ohel
hamet, ואין גוררין אותה בשבת בזמן שיש עליה מעות, ve'ein gorrin ota
beshabbat bizman sheyesh aleha maot, if there's money on the base, you
cannot drag the dresser. Okay, somehow if the base were considered one
unit with the dresser it would be more allowed, but for a
separate unit it's not allowed. We don't have to worry exactly about
that, but the point still is is that only when there's money
actively on the base can you not drag it, which sounds like
any other circumstance you can drag it even if there was money
on it בין השמשות. bein hashemashot. That's the same inference the גמרא
Gemara made a day or two ago. So the גמרא Gemara says
הא אין
עליה מעות שרי, ha ein aleha maot sharei, if there's no money
on it right now you can drag it, אף על גב דהוי
עליה בין השמשות af al gav dehavi aleha bein hashemashot even though
it was on בין השמשות. bein hashemashot. So from this משנה mishna
about this very complicated vessel and its status, but we say that
the only time is when there's actively money on it. Now that
is similar to רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said
when the lamp is burning don't move it, okay, but he doesn't
have a problem if it was burning when שבת Shabbat began, and
this משנה mishna also, when there's money on it don't move it,
but presumably doesn't have a problem if there was money on it
when שבת Shabbat began. So that sounds like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon.
Now רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan says we normally go by a סתם
משנה. Stam Mishna. So we just got through trying to make it
clear yesterday and even today defend the idea that רבי יוחנן Rebbi
Yochanan holds like רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, not like רבי שמעון, Rebbi
Shimon, okay, and even though we might not have been able to
prove it from the מנורה Menorah case because maybe the מנורה Menorah
was a special reason, but at the end we say nevertheless we
established yesterday he holds like רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda. Here the סתם
משנה Stam Mishna sounds like רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon. So how can
he hold like רבי יהודה? Rebbi Yehuda? So let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רב זירא Amar
Rav Zeira
תהא משנתנו Tehey Mishnateinu דהוה עליה מעות Dehava Aleha Maot בין השמשות,
Bein Hashmashot, which is obviously, by the way, not even such a
big question. Yeah, the משנה Mishna says if there's money on it
now don't drag it, means because there wasn't money on it בין
השמשות. Bein Hashmashot. It's one scenario. One way you can't drag the
dresser is if there's money on it now. Another scenario you can't
drag the dresser is if there was money on it when שבת
Shabbos began, and there isn't money on it now. So you made
this big inference, oh, only because it's on it now. Not only
because it's on it now. If it weren't on it בין השמשות
Bein Hashmashot and it's on it now, that's one case. Another case
is it was on it בין השמשות, Bein Hashmashot, so don't go
proving from this משנה Mishna like רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon. And now
it's a very interesting way he ends this phrase: שלא לשבור דבריו
של רבי יוחנן, Shelo lishbor devarav shel Rebbi Yochanan, to not break
the ruling of רבי יוחנן. Rebbi Yochanan. רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan said,
at least we concluded yesterday, we go like רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda,
not like רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon. How does that fit with his
general position you go like a סתם משנה? Stam Mishna? I'm going
to give you an answer that's maybe not an answer you'll get
so excited about, but it's a necessary answer to protect the words
of רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan that he shouldn't be contradicting himself. Okay,
so it's actually an interesting phrase לשבור, lishbor, like break, to shatter,
which is not, it's not so common. Anyway, so then we've wrapped
that up. Okay, it's so funny, like two pages trying to figure
out, two דפים, dappim, figure out how do various people hold vis-a-vis
רבי יוחנן. Rebbi Yochanan. So we've said now vis-a-vis רבי שמעון: Rebbi
Shimon: רב Rav holds like רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, רבי יוחנן Rebbi
Yochanan holds like רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, רבי Rebbi who sounded like
he held like רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, maybe he holds like רבי
יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda. You see the thrust of the גמרא Gemara to
move away from רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon. Okay, and now the גמרא
Gemara is going to continue. אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, Amar Rebbi
Yehoshua Ben Levi, said רבי יהושע בן לוי: Rebbi Yehoshua Ben Levi:
פעם אחת הלך רבי לדיוספרא. Pa'am achat halach Rebbi l'Diospora. Now this
has got to mean diaspora. How do they translate it there in
the English? Do they translate it? They don't? Diospora,
they think it's a place, they don't think, right, רש"י Rashi says
it's מקום, makom, but it sounds so much like diaspora, you know?
It's the town of Diospora.
Oh, too bad. Alright, anyway, רבי Rebbi once went
there והורה במנורה כרבי שמעון בנר. v'horah b'menorah k'Rebbi Shimon b'ner. And
he ruled regarding a מנורה Menorah like רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon rules
by the נר. ner. Now רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon rules by the
lamp that it's okay, it's not מוקצה muktzeh if it's not burning.
And he ruled the same way by the מנורה. Menorah. So that
whole issue we had before about a מנורה Menorah with engravings that
looks like it's of pieces and lit, and that seemed a little
far-fetched, the גמרא Gemara is saying גזירה לגזירה, gezeira l'gezeira, feel good,
רבי Rebbi said you could be lenient by the מנורה Menorah like
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon said by the lamp. Now the גמרא Gemara
has a question. איבעיא להו, Iba'ya lehu, they raised the
question: הורה במנורה כרבי שמעון בנר להתירא? Horah b'menorah k'Rebbi Shimon b'ner
l'heteira? Did he rule like מנורה Menorah the way רבי שמעון Rebbi
Shimon ruled by the lamp and said it was
permissible? או דילמא הורה במנורה לאיסורא וכרבי שמעון בנר להתירא? O dilma
horah b'menorah l'issura u'k'Rebbi Shimon b'ner l'heteira? It was two rulings. He
ruled by the מנורה Menorah like everything we've been saying until now,
that מנורה Menorah is off-limits, and he ruled like רבי שמעון Rebbi
Shimon that by the lamp it's okay. So it's not like the
same ruling, he ruled by the מנורה Menorah the same way רבי
שמעון Rebbi Shimon ruled by the lamp and they're both okay. No,
he ruled by the מנורה Menorah its way, it's forbidden, and he
ruled like רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon by a lamp that a lamp
is okay. So the גמרא Gemara says תיקו. teiku. So we don't
know the answer to that. Okay, and we also don't know whether
when he ruled like רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon by the lamp, was
that just a ruling by the lamp or was it a more
across-the-board ruling like רבי שמעון? Rebbi Shimon? Okay, so that is again
unclear about the מנורה Menorah a little bit and now also and
also unclear about about רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this: רב
מלכיה איקלע לבי רב שמלאי. Rav Malkia ikla l'bei Rav Simlai. רב
מלכיה Rav Malkia came to the house of רב שמלאי Rav Simlai
וטלטל שרגא, v'tiltal shraga, and he moved a lamp, okay, after obviously
extinguished, but anyway that's the way רש"י Rashi explains it, extinguished. Okay,
again, which would at least be in one way like רבי שמעון,
Rebbi Shimon, maybe not across the board but at least by the
lamp it's like רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon. ואיקפד רב שמלאי, V'ikpad Rav
Simlai, and רב שמלאי Rav Simlai got upset, said we don't do
that around here, we don't move a lamp after it's gone out,
and this is my house, house rules. רבי יוסי גלילאי, Rebbi Yose
Glilai, רבי יוסי Rebbi Yose of the Galilee, איקלע לאתריה דרבי יוסי
ברבי חנינא, ikla l'atrei d'Rebbi Yose b'Rebbi Chanina, he came to the
house of רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא. Rebbi Yose b'Rebbi Chanina. טלטל שרגא,
Tiltal shraga, he moved a lamp after it went out, ואיקפד רבי
יוסי ברבי חנינא, v'ikpad Rebbi Yose b'Rebbi Chanina, רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא
Rebbi Yose b'Rebbi Chanina got upset. So again you see like the
position of רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon is like resurfacing, it's not completely
being, you know, being dismissed, it's not completely disappearing, but the גמרא
Gemara constantly is talking about this move to go against רבי שמעון.
Rebbi Shimon. Okay, this move to rule against him that you don't
move the lamp after it's gone out. it's gone out. One minute.
So the גמרא Gemara says כי איכא לאסרי דרבי יוחנן. ki ika
le'asrei de'Rabbi Yochanan.
I'm sorry did I skip a line? רבי אבהו, Rabbi Abahu, רבי
אבהו, Rabbi Abahu, כי איכא לאסרי דרבי יהושע בן לוי, ki ika
le'asrei de'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, when he came to the house of
רבי יהושע בן לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, הוי מטלטל שרגא, havie
metalteil shraga, he would move a lamp. אבל כי אתא לאסרי דרבי
יוחנן, aval ki ata le'asrei de'Rabbi Yochanan, when he came to the
house of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, לא הוי מטלטל שרגא, lo havie
metalteil shraga, he would not move a lamp. Now we had just
established before that רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, right, is like רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda. So let's take a look. אטו ממה נפשך, ato mima
nafshach, make up your mind. אי כרבי יהודה סבירא ליה, ei ke'Rabbi
Yehuda sevira lei, if he holds like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, ליעבד
כרבי יהודה, le'aveid ke'Rabbi Yehuda, let him consistently act like רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda and move the lamp after it goes out. אי כרבי
שמעון סבירא ליה, ei ke'Rabbi Shimon sevira lei, if he holds like
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, ליעבד כרבי שמעון, le'aveid ke'Rabbi Shimon, let him
consistently move the lamp—I mean, let him consistently move the lamp, why
in one place did he and in one place he didn't? So
the גמרא Gemara says, לעולם כרבי שמעון סבירא ליה. le'olam ke'Rabbi Shimon
sevira lei. He basically held it was allowed, ומשום כבודו דרבי יוחנן,
umishum kevodo de'Rabbi Yochanan, but when he was in רבי יוחנן's Rabbi
Yochanan place, out of respect and deference to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
הוא דלא הוי עביד, hu dela havie avid, so
therefore he would not move it. Which obviously you can't say basically
he held it was forbidden and when he was in the other
rabbi's place he moved it. If it's forbidden then you don't do
it, but if it's basically allowed you can choose not to do
it, which he therefore would do out of respect. So again we
are seeing different positions here about people that would act like רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon or not like רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, but even
here it's in the limited question of the lamp when it went
out, right? And that's before it was even like you generally say
like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon no מוקצה muktzah at all. Here at
most what's being sort of debated at this stage is a much
narrower thing. Can we at least rule like him by the lamp
case to say after it's gone out you can move it. Yes,
Charlie.
I'm surprised these first two rabbis would come into another rabbi's house
and do something that the rabbi held was אסור. asur. I mean,
isn't it דרך ארץ derech eretz to follow the ruling?
Maybe he didn't know. You know,
maybe he did what he was used to and then he found
out otherwise, you know, I don't know, it's not clear yet.
Why would he be so?
Maybe he thought the other rabbi was more of a pluralist, I
don't know. Yes.
What's the reason? If רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, you know, has a
basic global position, why just limit it to one case of a
נר? ner? Okay, we can hold like him by נר ner and
anything else in terms of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and מוקצה.
muktzah. I'm sorry? Oh, because
well, because the basic position... why could you rule like רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon just by the נר ner case and not more globally?
Because they're not necessarily connected. Meaning the issue with the נר ner
is two things. Why does רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon more lenient? And
this gives me an opportunity to mention a point תוספות... Tosafot... what
I meant to mention about תוספות. Tosafot. Why does רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon lenient by the נר ner when it goes out? Well, it
could just be one reason that you don't like the candle, the
lamp, after it's been used, it's מחמת מיאוס. machmat mi'us. It's that
the lantern is like disgusting, it's pottery that's been used, once it's
disgusting. That's even if it wasn't burning when שבת Shabbat began. So
not everybody holds of the category of מחמת מיאוס. machmat mi'us. We're
actually going to get in a few minutes to discuss cases about
that. Either you might not hold the category altogether, how מיאוס mi'us
is מיאוס? mi'us? You know, I mean, my God, I use it
every day to light a candle, it can't be that מיאוס, mi'us,
right? So maybe you just don't hold of it. Now the other
question is what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon also also seems to say
was even if it was burning when שבת Shabbat began. That's a
separate question. Does the status of something בין השמשות bein hashemashot when
שבת Shabbat begins determine the status for the whole שבת? Shabbat? So
we generally say yes, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says no. But you
could agree with those two points: I don't hold of the category
of מחמת מיאוס machmat mi'us and I don't hold that when שבת
Shabbat begins it determines its status, but you could still hold of
every other case of מוקצה. muktzah. The גמרא Gemara took that רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon and started making very global statements. רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon holds of absolutely no מוקצה muktzah except maybe this one case
and that one case and so on. So now that's a different
question. What motivated the גמרא Gemara to say that? Okay? So that's
the question. Maybe there's some other cases that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says other things about rejecting מוקצה, muktzah, but just because you don't
hold of the lamp case doesn't mean you reject מוקצה muktzah altogether.
So that's an important thing to mention from the shift. Yesterday the
question was maybe we have an opinion that rules like רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon and completely rejects מוקצה. muktzah. By today we seem to
have moved beyond that. Nobody's completely rejecting מוקצה. muktzah. But maybe do
we rule like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon by at least the lamp
case after it's gone out? Now תוספות Tosafot says that actually even
here the גמרא Gemara isn't discussing when it was burning בין השמשות.
bein hashemashot. The גמרא Gemara is assuming that everybody also rejects רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon that when it was burning when שבת Shabbat began
it remains off limits. And the whole discussion here is a lamp
that was used in the past that wasn't being used on this
שבת. Shabbat. And the whole discussion here is the מיאוס mi'us case.
It's a lamp that might be too yukky and disgusting and that's
it. But if it was burning when שבת Shabbat began, nobody is
going to rule like that position of רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. That's
the way תוספות Tosafot reads it, okay? So again a very narrowing
of the degree to which we're willing to discuss might you go
like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Certainly not about מוקצה muktzah altogether who
he rejects it. We do not say that. We accept מוקצה muktzah
in broad cases. Number two, maybe by the lamp. So רש"י Rashi
says maybe even it was burning when שבת Shabbat began, maybe that
we can accept his position. תוספות Tosafot says no, no, no. At
most we're discussing that you had not used the lamp at all
on שבת Shabbat began, then it would remain מוקצה muktzah for שבת
Shabbat and the question is maybe just we don't hold of the
issue of it being disgusting. Yes.
But is that clear from the... how does it work? Is that
what תוספות Tosafot says? Is that right? Is that what the...
You mean how do I know what the גמרא's Gemara talking about
if you can interpret it either way? You never know! That's why
there's debates of ראשונים Rishonim and debates in הלכה Halacha because the
גמרא's Gemara never fully clear.
Yes. What do you say about תוספות? Tosafot? Right.
And I wasn't. I was explaining it רש"י's Rashi way. So actually
it's worth pointing out, which is that we normally actually embed רש"י's
Rashi interpretation in the גמרא, Gemara, that becomes the norm, and then
your תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות's Tosafot like changing the meaning of the גמרא.
Gemara. But it's actually many times not true, I mean maybe תוספות
Tosafot was the פשט Pshat and רש"י Rashi was a forced read,
and just often the one you normally, you have to have a
baseline, right. Actually חיים סולובייצ'יק Chaim Soveichik made this point about he
says תוספות Tosafot which he does like this whole critical commentary, you
can't have a critical commentary until you have a baseline interpretation of
the גמרא Gemara or else you're trying to hit a moving target.
You have to be able to like say, okay, if the גמרא's
Gemara saying this, what about this, what about this, and then oh,
maybe the גמרא Gemara actually means something else. But you can only
have that conversation if you start with some baseline interpretation. So רש"י
Rashi provides the baseline and then תוספות Tosafot says no, but actually
it makes better sense to read it this way. But that doesn't
mean רש"י Rashi is necessarily more פשט. Pshat. Yes.
So how do you read this? You think they're talking about a
lamp that wasn't...
I have no way of knowing
that answer. I'm saying there's no internal evidence about that. Now actually
we're about to get to a discussion about מוקצה מחמת מיאוס. Muktzah
Machmat Miyus. Now that might support תוספות Tosafot that the whole previous
discussion is מוקצה מחמת מיאוס, Muktzah Machmat Miyus, but again, who knows.
This, מר
בר אמימר, Mar bar Ameimar, exactly. So that's exactly it, sometimes you
don't know what the גמרא's Gemara exactly talking about. That's why the
debates are so giant.
And one of the reasons ירושלמי Yerushalmi is so difficult is there's
no רש"י Rashi and it's very often unclear what the גמרא's...
Gemara Yeah, that is true. I mean it's difficult for other internal
reasons as well, but that certainly adds to the difficulty that we
don't have a good baseline interpretation. Yes, Seth.
And are all of them lined up just around the... and it
makes a distinction between נר Ner and מנורה? Menorah?
Yes, מנורה Menorah is a נר Ner is like a little lamp.
It's that picture on the שטיינזלץ גמרא, Steinsaltz Gemara, right? And the
מנורה Menorah is like literally a candelabra.
Not talking about in terms of חנוכה, Chanukah, but
a מנורה.
Menorah. Right. A מנורה Menorah is the issue that even if we're
generally lenient, right exactly, even if we're generally lenient by a lamp
in various circumstances, whether it was burning, wasn't burning, we're not going
to be so lenient by a מנורה Menorah because you'll come to
fix it and the whole מכה בפטיש Makeh B'patish type of issues.
Exactly. Exactly, yes. Let's take a look as the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
By the way, it is interesting because here it says not moving
the lamp and the bottom of the דף, Daf, if you remember,
it says רבי יוחנן Rav Yochanan says we rule like רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon at least by the lamp that you can move. Okay,
so it's a little
interesting why here we actually have that in the place of רבי
יוחנן Rav Yochanan they weren't moving the lamp out of deference to
רבי יוחנן. Rav Yochanan. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara now continues. It says
like this. אמר
רב יהודה. Amar Rav Yehuda. So רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said: שרגא
דמשחא שרי לטלטולה. Sharga d'mishcha shari l'tiltula. A lamp of oil, an
oil lamp, you can move it. Okay. Presumably it's not burning now.
Whether it was burning when שבת Shabbos began is not clear, but
again, that's to some degree the debate we just mentioned. But now
it seems like it's really focused just on the מיאוס Miyus category.
So even if presumably if it wasn't burning, we're talking. So if
you have fine, an oil lamp, you can move it. That's not
a מיאוס Miyus case. Let's bracket the issue of whether it was
burning. Let's assume it wasn't burning when שבת Shabbos began. דנפטא, D'nafta,
if it's of נפטא, Nafta, which is a very smelly type of
a pitch fuel, אסור לטלטולה, assur l'tiltula, you cannot move it because
that everybody would agree is מאוס. Ma'us. I don't disagree with the
category, there is a category מוקצה מחמת מיאוס. Muktzah Machmat Miyus. I
just say an oil lamp isn't in the category, but a נפטא
Nafta lamp, that is. רבא ורב יוסף דאמרי תרוייהו. Rava v'Rav Yosef
d'amri duvayhu. רבא Rava and רב יוסף Rav Yosef say: דנפטא נמי
שרי לטלטולה. D'nafta nami shari l'tiltula.
That you can also move. Now why is it? Do they reject
the category of מיאוס? Miyus? תוספות Tosafot says no, he says actually
there's a difference between being smelly and being disgusting. So sometimes things
are disgusting because they are smelly, but okay. But תוספות Tosafot says
it's not like it's disgusting to handle. Yes, it has a bad
smell, but it's not disgusting to handle and therefore that also isn't
in the מאוס. Ma'us. So we agree to the מאוס Ma'us category,
but we define it very narrowly. רב אביא Rav Avya איקלע לבי
רבא. ikla l'bei Rava. רב אביא Rav Avya came to the house
of רבא. Rava. הוו מאיסן בכרעי בטינא. Hava me'isin b'karei bitina. So
we're talking about מאוס, Ma'us, this seems to be like the theme.
So he actually רב אביא Rav Avya his legs got dirty in
mud, he was walking to his house and he walked through a
big mud puddle and apparently his mother never told him to wipe
your feet before coming into the house. So אספיה אפוריא קמיה דרבא.
aspay a puraya kmei d'Rava. He sat on the bed in front
of רבא Rava or the couch and with his muddy
legs. So איקפיד רבא. ikpid Rava. רבא Rava got upset. Before he
got upset because somebody was moving מוקצה, Muktzah, here he's upset because
he's ruining his nice couch. So בעי לצעורי. ba l'tzu'arei. So he
wanted to give him a hard time. You come to my house,
you have with your muddy feet and you sit on my
couch. אמר ליה, Amar lei, מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? רבא ורב יוסף
דאמרי תרוייהו... Rava v'Rav Yosef d'amri duvayhu... why do רבא Rava and
רב יוסף Rav Yosef both say... רבא Rava says this to his
guest. guest here who's muddying up his couch to רב אויא, Rav
Avaya, why do רב Rav and רב יוסף Rav Yosef both say
שרגא דנפתא נמי שרי לטלטולי, sharga de-nefta nami shari letiltulei, that you
can even move a lamp of naphtha? Now again, I'm just reading
this in the גמרא Gemara but I imagine there it's not a
coincidence that he asks him a question about מיאוס, mius, right? And
he was probably saying to him like, "Why do you think they
said that? I mean isn't it disgusting and you don't like handling
disgusting things in your house? Hint, hint." Anyway, so אמר ליה, amlei,
so he said back to him, he either intentionally or unintentionally refused
to pick up the hint, הואיל וחזי לכסויי בי מנא, hoil ve-chazei
le-khisuyei bei mana,
since you can still use things even after they're disgusting, you can
cover it with a... you can cover a vessel with it. You've
got this disgusting naphtha lamp, so you might not want to use
it, I don't know, to adorn your table, but you might want
to use it to like somehow seal up some vessel. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אלא מעתה, ella meiata, if that's true, כל צרורות
שבחצר, kol tzerorot shebe-chatzer, then the גמרא Gemara is... oh,
it seems like רבא Rava is answering this because then he's on
deck. All rocks in the field, מטלטלין, metaltelin, you should be able
to just move a rock, הואיל וחזי לכסויי בי מנא, hoil ve-chazei
le-khisuyei bei mana, since you could use the rock to like seal
up some hole in a vessel. So I mean, you know, come
on, then we wouldn't hold of basic מוקצה. muktzeh. I mean rocks
are מוקצה. muktzeh. You can always find some use for something. So
אמר ליה, amlei, he said back to him, האי איכא תורת כלי
עליה הני ליכא תורת כלי עליה. hai ika torat keli aleiha hani
leika torat keli aleiha. There's a big difference if something is a
vessel or isn't a vessel. If it's a vessel, it basically means
it's created for human use, it's set aside for use. So in
order to get it out of the category of use, it has
to become completely off limits. So even if something is smelly and
disgusting and I wouldn't normally use it, it doesn't... if there are
some uses I might still have for it, for me that's not
מוקצה. muktzeh. That is different than a rock, because a rock never
came into the category of things that I would use and therefore...
now I can, by the way, make a rock not מוקצה, muktzeh,
I can make a paperweight, but if I haven't brought it into
sort of the human realm, right, then it remains... then it started
מוקצה muktzeh and it remains מוקצה. muktzeh. This, which started as a
vessel, requires a lot more to get it out of that category.
So מי לא תניא, mi lo tanya, one minute, have we not
taught in a ברייתא, baraita, השירים והנזמים והטבעות, hashirim ve-hanezamim ve-hatabaot, various
types of bracelets, נזמים, nezamim, thank you, nose rings and rings. Now
these are things which we are going to learn in an upcoming
פרק, perek, that they did not allow people to wear certain types
of jewelry, women and men, with a focus on women, on שבת
Shabbat outside of, you know, in a space that did not have
an עירוב, eruv, outside of a חצר, chatzer, in a street, because
of a concern that they would take it off and show it
to people. By the way, in places where they don't have an
עירוב, eruv, there's a... there's a מנהג, minhag, I don't know if
it's like universally accepted, but there's a מנהג minhag of not wearing
gloves even on a cold day, because in places where you would
meet somebody, you'd take off your glove and shake the hand and
then you'd have your glove in your hand and you might forget
and walk with it, which makes it really hard if you live
in cold climates without a... cold climates without an עירוב. eruv. Anyway,
that's going to be an upcoming פרק. perek. So it says, ah,
but what if you have these pieces of jewelry and you're in
your חצר? chatzer? You're in your yard that's surrounded by walls, there's
no carrying problem, can you still move them? Okay, now maybe they
didn't... there's a question, they might not have allowed you to wear
them even in your חצר, chatzer, because if we let you wear
it in your חצר, chatzer, you're going to, you know, in your
yard, you're going to step out onto the street. Okay, so גזירה
לגזירה gezeira le-gezeira and all that, but fine, that's what they said.
So you can't wear them, but can you move them around in
your yard? Or do we say no, since they can't be worn,
they have no use and they're מוקצה? muktzeh? So it says, הרי
הן ככל הכלים הניטלין בחצר, harei hen ke-khol ha-kelim ha-nitalin be-chatzer, like
all other types of vessels, you can move them, you can't wear
them. ואמר עולא, ve-amar Ulla, מה טעם, ma taam,
what's the reason? הואיל ואיכא תורת כלי עליה, hoil ve-ika torat keli
aleiha, because it's still a vessel. Meaning, what else... what are you
going to do with jewelry other than wear it? But nevertheless, once
it's a vessel, it's really hard to get it to becoming מוקצה.
muktzeh. So even though you're not allowed to wear this, it's not
מוקצה. muktzeh. הכא נמי, hacha nami, here too, הואיל ואיכא תורת כלי
עליה, hoil ve-ika torat keli aleiha, once it's a vessel, it makes
it much more resistant to becoming מוקצה. muktzeh. Now obviously there are
vessels that are מוקצה, muktzeh, you know, מחמת חסרון כיס, machmat chisaron
kis, like my Ming vase, you know, that I told you or
other types of things that are types of vessels that are completely
off limits. But the point is, it's not just because it's hard
to find a use, it's really... once it starts life as a
vessel, it requires a lot to get it out of that category
of usability and be considered מוקצה. muktzeh. So he said, basically he
says, either I don't hold of מוקצה מחמת מיאוס muktzeh machmat mius
at all, or basically I have a very narrowly defined category. It
has to be so disgusting that you would never want to use
it for anything, but if... or for anything you could do on
שבת, Shabbos, but if you can find some use for it still
on שבת, Shabbos, I'm not going to call it מוקצה מחמת מיאוס.
muktzeh machmat mius. And that's what he said, ignoring the fact that
he was ruining the couch. Now right at the... the גמרא Gemara
ends by
saying, אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, בריך
רחמנא דלא כספיה רבא לרב אויא. barich rachmana dela chasfyei Rava le-Rav
Avaya. Thank... ברוך השם Baruch Hashem that רבא Rava did not embarrass
רב אויא. Rav Avaya. Was it ברוך השם Baruch Hashem because it's
not nice to embarrass someone, or ברוך השם Baruch Hashem because now
we've got a good answer to this question? Yes, let's go.
So this reminds me of what we had before, right? About the
trumpet and like the Gampel volcano.
Right, exactly. That's a good... Example. And the issue with the trumpets,
so as the גמרא Gemara says, is does it become so sort
of set aside for that one use that you consider it to
have no legitimate use other than that on שבת? Shabbat? And here
the גמרא Gemara is saying you do have a legitimate use. You
can maybe you know that you would use it. A trumpet you're
not going to use to stop up a hole in a wine
barrel. But this type of a of a lamp you might actually
use for that purpose. Okay? Alright. So now that is the question
about do we hold of the category of מוקצה מחמת מיאוס? muktzeh
machmas miyus? We seem to be moving beyond רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon,
focusing on the issue of a lamp that wasn't used this שבת,
Shabbat, was used in the past. Do we hold of מוקצה מחמת
מיאוס? muktzeh machmas miyus? Maybe only a very narrow category, maybe not
at all. Yes?
What could you use a bracelet for?
A bracelet for? Well, first of all, there's always the question of
can you look at it to like just look at it, to
look at it to appreciate it? Like can I take out my
photo album and show it to you on שבת, Shabbat, right? I
mean I'm not doing anything with the pictures but I am like
looking at them.
You know,
I don't know, it's a good question. What other use might you
have for a trumpet on שבת? Shabbat? Right, because the trumpet, you
know... oh you mean that's a good question. Like let's say I
wanted to show you my trumpet to just show you what a
what a gorgeous trumpet I have. Yeah, that's a you know it
is an interesting question about that in general. Like is to look
at something... I think there's a difference, meaning I think that you
know things like a photo album and I'd have to check. Like
you know I'm sure this gets discussed because מוקצה muktzeh is a
huge category so every permutation gets discussed. But basically a photo album
it's like primarily there for being used and jewelry as well. The
whole reason the גמרא... Gemara... for being looked at. The whole reason
the גמרא Gemara sort of had a problem with wearing jewelry is
you would take it off in order to show it. So it's
a type of thing that people actually handle specifically for the purpose
of looking at it and inspecting and appreciating and so on. So
I imagine if the trumpet were in that category like everybody's always
going around showing each other their musical instruments and how gorgeous they
are then I imagine that that could be a difference as well.
Yes.
So what's the problem with taking it off?
By the way, the trumpet was debated. I mean some people say
that you know... but anyway yeah.
נזם Nezm is always... נזם Nezm is always a nose ring...
wants to take him off for a nose ring. נזם? Nezm? No,
this is that it's already off and you're not wearing it and
you're looking at it off. Yes.
So what's the problem with taking it off, from not setting it
down, I'm not handing it to another person, I'm not carrying it?
I just take it off, show someone, and then put it right
back on.
There'd be no problem. But the problem is that you'll take it
off and show and then you'll keep having it in your hand
and keep on carrying. Right, so there's a lot of גזירות gzeiros
here. Maybe you'll take it off and forget to put it back
on and by the way don't even wear it in your courtyard
because you'll come to step out into the street. So yes, they
tend to make a lot of גזירה לגזירה. gzeira le'gzeira. Okay now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. רמי ליה אביי לרבא. Rami lei
Abaye le'Rava. So
אביי Abaye asked רבא. Rava. תניא, Tanya, we taught in a ברייתא.
braisa. מותר השמן שבנר ושבקערה אסור רבי
שמעון מתיר.
Mosar hashemen shebaner ve'shebekara assur, Rabbi
Shimon matir. Okay, back to רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. The leftover oil
that's in the lamp or in the plate is forbidden, but רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon allows it once it's not currently burning. And right
now the only reason we've given that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon has
a problem when it's currently burning is מוקצה למצוה. muktzeh le'mitzvah. Okay,
we'll see another reason coming up. But anyway the left... once it
stops burning the oil is okay. אלמא לרבי שמעון לית ליה מוקצה.
Alma le'Rabbi Shimon leisei muktzeh. So we hear he doesn't hold of
מוקצה. muktzeh. Again, it's an interesting generalization. Doesn't hold of מוקצה muktzeh
at all? But anyway at least he doesn't hold the מוקצה muktzeh
that when something was burning when שבת Shabbos began, was אסור assur
when שבת Shabbos began, it should remain מוקצה muktzeh for all of
שבת. Shabbos. So ורמינהו, uraminhu, I'll ask you on this. רבי שמעון
אומר. Rabbi Shimon omer. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says: כל שאין מומו
ניכר מערב יום טוב אין זה מן המוכן. Kol she'ein mumo nikar
me'erev Yom Tov, ein ze min hamuchan. That you have a בכור,
bechor, you have a firstborn cow or calf or sheep. And the
הלכה halacha is like this: if it has a blemish, maybe you
even gave it to a כהן. Kohen. The כהן, Kohen, however, can
only bring it as a קרבן. korban. Okay, but if it has
a blemish he can שחט shecht it outside of the בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash. He can שחט shecht it like straight. He doesn't even
need to redeem it. It's a special category of something that without
a blemish you bring it as a קרבן, korban, with a blemish
you eat it even without redeeming it. Now, so on יום טוב
Yom Tov you can שחט shecht things. So can you שחט shecht
this בכור? bechor? Well, if the blemish was seen before יום טוב,
Yom Tov, was obvious before יום טוב, Yom Tov, then you knew
when יום טוב Yom Tov began you would be able to שחט
shecht it and eat it and it was like an animal that
you could have had in mind and therefore you can שחט shecht
it on יום טוב. Yom Tov. But if you did not notice
the blemish before יום טוב, Yom Tov, then it was a בכור
bechor that you thought was off-limits, so therefore it remains off-limits for
all of יום טוב Yom Tov even if there is a blemish
that you discover on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Okay? So that's what
that's what we say. And that's רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. כל שאין
מומו ניכר מערב יום טוב, Kol she'ein mumo nikar me'erev Yom Tov,
if the blemish was not obvious before יום טוב Yom Tov before
יום טוב, Yom Tov, אין זה מן המוכן, ein ze min hamuchan,
it is not considered designated, set aside, prepared, and therefore you cannot
eat it even if you see even if you see the blemish
on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So by the way, I should mention
that תוספות Tosafos points out that there's a whole debate also you
know
about in מסכת ביצה Masechet Beitza about whether you're allowed to, forgetting
מוקצה muktzeh issues, are you allowed to look at the blemish on
יום טוב Yom Tov and give a ruling about the blemish on
יום טוב? Yom Tov? That's like a separate debate. Like there are
things you're not supposed to do, like you're not supposed to have...
דין, din, sit in a court case, can you give a ruling
on a בכור bechor on יום טוב Yom Tov and such, even
if the blemish was there from beforehand? Okay,
but here the phrase is, the way we know that's not the
point, it's not saying you're not allowed to inspect it because the
phrase used is אינו מן המוכן, eino min hamuchan, and מוכן muchan
is the phrase meaning it's the opposite of מוקצה. muktzeh. מוקצה muktzeh
is להקצות, lehaktzos, to like set aside, to push away, and מוכן
muchan is prepared. So when he says it's not מן המוכן, min
hamuchan, it's a מוקצה muktzeh problem. So you see Rabbi Shimon holds
if it was off-limits when יום טוב Yom Tov began, it remains
off-limits. How is that consistent with the burning lamp? So the גמרא
Gemara says הכי השתא. hachi hasha. What, how can you compare these
cases? התם, hasam, over
there, אדם יושב ומצפה אימתי תכבה נרו, adam yoshev umitzappe imatai tichbe
nero, a person is sitting and waiting when his lamp will go
out. Now, not like you're really hoping it'll go out soon because
otherwise you wouldn't have lit it, but it means you anticipate that
it's going to go out and you're not expecting it to burn,
and maybe also you only want it to burn at night, you
don't want it to burn in the next morning. So there you
know when שבת Shabbos begins that it will burn out and there'll
be leftover oil and you want to use the leftover oil. And
that's why it's okay. But הכא hacha here, אדם יושב ומצפה אימתי
יפול בו מום? יפול בו מום? adam yoshev umitzappe imatai tippol bo
mum? Yippol bo mum? If a person has an unblemished בכור, bechor,
can he reasonably be expecting, oh well, I'll probably be able to
have this on יום טוב Yom Tov because a blemish will fall
in it? No, I mean מי אמר, mi amar, think of all
the things that have to happen for it to become fit for
him to use on יום טוב. Yom Tov. מי יימר דנפל ביה
מומא? mi yeimar denafal bei muma? Number one, who knows that there's
going to be a, it's going to get a blemish? He doesn't
even see the blemish before יום טוב. Yom Tov. And ואם תמצא
לומר דנפל ביה מומא, ve'im timtza lomar denafal bei muma, even if
there is a blemish there or it gets a blemish on יום
טוב, Yom Tov, מי יימר דנפל ביה מום קבוע? mi yeimar denafal
bei mum kavua? How do I know it'll be a permanent blemish?
An impermanent blemish doesn't do me any good, doesn't count. And ואם
תמצא לומר דנפל ביה מום קבוע, ve'im timtza lomar denafal bei mum
kavua, even if it's a permanent blemish, מי יימר דמזדקק ליה חכם?
mi yeimar dimizdakek leh chacham? Who knows that I'll be able to
get a חכם chacham to rule for me? Now תוספות Tosafos says
part of the reason you're not going to get a חכם chacham
to rule for you is because it's אסור assur to rule for
a בכור bechor on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Okay, so this is
Rabbi Shimon's position. So Rabbi Yehuda, תוספות Tosafos points out the irony,
Rabbi Yehuda normally holds of more מוקצה, muktzeh, holds that this isn't
מוקצה. muktzeh. Why? Because Rabbi Yehuda holds you're allowed to get somebody
to rule on a בכור bechor on יום טוב. Yom Tov. But
Rabbi Shimon says you're not allowed. So therefore, the likelihood that this
will become permissible to you, somebody will actually give you a ruling
when they're not supposed to and that it'll have a blemish, that's
very difficult. Now this by the way is similar to what we
said a few days ago, which is that even Rabbi Shimon does
hold there are cases when it's off-limits the beginning of the day,
it stays off-limits. Remember the גמרא Gemara way at the beginning distinguished
between a lamp that has a little oil or like, you know,
a big vessel that has a lot of oil. That if you
lit something with a big vessel with a lot of oil and
it was supposed to burn all of שבת Shabbos and by some
freak accident it went out, Rabbi Shimon would agree it's off-limits because
that's the type of thing that you were, you know, assuming would
remain off-limits all of שבת. Shabbos. So the גמרא Gemara here is
repeating that idea again. It's not like Rabbi Shimon doesn't hold of
any מוקצה. muktzeh. Okay, there are cases when it's off-limits when שבת
Shabbos begins, it remains מוקצה muktzeh in a case where under reasonable
circumstances it would have remained unusable. So that's a case of like
a lamp with a lot of oil or a case of this
בכור bechor when יום טוב Yom Tov begins, under most circumstances you
would not have had a reason to think you would be able
to use it on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara continues like this. מתיבי רמי בר חמא, matvi Rami bar
Chama, so רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama asked,
מפירין נדרים בשבת ונשאלין לנדרים שהן לצורך שבת. mafirin nedarim beShabbos ve-nish'alin
lenedarim shehen letzoirech Shabbos. A husband can annul his wife's vows. A
husband is allowed to annul his wife's vows
within the day that he hears of them if they are relating
to like impact him as opposed to if they only impact the
wife. And so that's מפירין נדרים, mafirin nedarim, you can do that
on שבת. Shabbos. And if you made a vow
and you can go to a חכם chacham and get a ruling
that, you know, based on that had you known you wouldn't have
made it based on various considerations like we do התרת נדרים hataras
nedarim like we do, you know, on ערב ראש השנה. Erev Rosh
Hashanah. So you can do that also on שבת, Shabbos, שהן לצורך
שבת, shehen letzoirech Shabbos, if there's a שבת Shabbos need for it.
Like you made a vow that says you're not going to eat,
you know, a certain fruit or טשולנט cholent or whatever and, you
know, now you want to get that annulled or you want to
get
the husband to annul it or somebody else to annul your vow,
and you're allowed to do it if it's serving the שבת Shabbos
purposes. So now the גמרא Gemara says, now apparently though it's not
a מוקצה muktzeh issue. Now why is it not a מוקצה muktzeh
issue? If the thing you have to know about a vow, different
from an oath, is that an oath relates to the person. I
forbid myself from eating טשולנט. cholent. So that's hard to imagine that
that's relevant to מוקצה. muktzeh. Once I get it annulled, okay, the
טשולנט cholent was never מוקצה, muktzeh, I was off-limits to it but
it wasn't somehow as an object, you know, forbidden. Although maybe yes,
it separates me from the object, for me it's מוקצה. muktzeh. But
vows are anyway different. Vows are the טשולנט cholent becomes אסור. assur.
Okay, and I can even make my טשולנט cholent אסור assur on
you. Okay, and Okay, so it's the actual object that becomes forbidden.
That's more like if that object was off-limits as the object was
forbidden when שבת Shabbos began, then even when I change the status
now, how does it become un-מוקצה? un-muktzeh? Okay, that's the question. Now
תוספות Tosafos has an interesting issue which is right about if something
is forbidden to me, does it also become מוקצה muktzeh to you?
And that's something we're going to look at tomorrow as well about
if something for one person isn't usable for another person is, there's
a great question I'll actually I want to review this tomorrow before
we do the דף, daf, but somebody basically says if I פסקן
pasken smoking is אסור assur on יום טוב—on Yom Tov שבת Shabbos
everybody פסקנס paskens it's אסור assur on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Right,
the whole question about smoking is that you're making a fire and
normally we only allow that if it's something that's לצורך אוכל נפש
letzorech ochel nefesh of common, you know, of universal type of benefit.
So cooking and food and you know we discussed before bathing with
hot water, but smoking—so there was a time when people really believed
that smoking was, you know, was was helpful, salubrious to your health
and so on, so that everyone—oh it's a צורך כל הגוף tzorech
kol haguf etc., etc. Anyway, now because obviously of everything we know
about smoking, you know, you know, there's many positions, it seems like
the only reasonable one, but okay, that smoking is אסור assur on
יום טוב, Yom Tov, right, how do you justify, you know, doing
something like this that's injurious to the health? והישמרתם מאוד לנפשותיכם v'nishmartem
me'od l'nafshoseichem too, but at least on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Anyway,
but some people say it's still מותר muttar at least for somebody
who already is a smoker, you know, if you—a sub-category of the
people that are smokers for them it's an important thing, you know,
to feed their addiction or whatever to to satisfy this craving on
יום טוב. Yom Tov. Anyway, so there's that debate. So let's say
you are a smoker and you're smoking there on יום טוב, Yom
Tov, can I hand—can I handle your cigarettes? Okay? Or can I
handle my, you know, cigarettes that aren't yours? Because for you they're
not מוקצה, muktzeh, for me they are מוקצה. muktzeh. Okay? So how
do you deal with something that's מוקצה muktzeh for one person not
for another? Does that get an objective status for everybody, you know,
or does it get defined by the person or the sub-class? So
to some degree this is the question here. This food is only
forbidden to me, is it מוקצה muktzeh to you? Is it מוקצה
muktzeh to me? Maybe it's not מוקצה muktzeh to you, maybe it's
also not מוקצה muktzeh to me? Okay, but anyway, so we'll read
the תוספות Tosafos in a minute he raises that issue. But for
now let's look at the גמרא'ס Gemara's question. It says like this.
So why can't it—it assumes that at least for me it's מוקצה.
muktzeh. Why is that allowed according to רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? Now
I don't know why somehow we assumed that this is רבי שמעון,
Rabbi Shimon, but we do. So why is that allowed? Why don't
we say that, you know, why don't we say that—I'm sorry. No,
no, no. The opposite. Excuse me, excuse me, hold on. So there
it says that it is allowed,
which works for רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, right, right, I'm sorry. So
why is it any different than the case of the בכור? bechor?
דאמאי de'amai why is that allowed? לימא מי יימר דמזדקק ליה
בעל—who leima mi yeimar demizdakak lei baal says that the husband will
agree to annul it? Or who says the חכם chacham will agree
to annul it? So we're going to deal with them one by
one. Okay? So if the בכור bechor even רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says the בכור bechor is off-limits because you can't assume that you're
going to get a חכם chacham to rule on it, so then
here why is this okay? Should be the same issue. Who can
say you'll get the husband to annul? I'm assuming the husband is
around.
So there's a big difference.
So first of all תוספות Tosafos says—well right, so first of all
תוספות Tosafos says you see by the way the idea of who
says a blemish will occur, you know, and is not the issue
because here it assumes that even only one doubt, who says I'll
find the husband and get him to annul, is enough to make
it off-limits. So תוספות Tosafos says right because we're even including cases
where it actually did have a blemish before יום טוב. Yom Tov.
And even so the very fact that I can't count on a
חכם chacham to annul makes it off-limits even for רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon. So certainly everybody should agree that is sufficient. So why here
is it different for the husband? But the answer is different. Not
just the husband's more available, which is true, but the answer is
as I said before, the חכם chacham is not allowed to rule
by the בכור. bechor. Okay, here you're allowed to rule, so obviously
there's a big difference.
One thing he's מזדקק. mizdakak.
I understand. All right. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says, but that
means how you know he'll agree to the the request. The husband
doesn't have to agree to annul, okay? But even though the husband
doesn't have to agree to annul, there's a big difference of maybe
he won't agree to the case by the בכור bechor where you're
not allowed to give a ruling on a בכור bechor on יום
טוב. Yom Tov. So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara
says חסורי מיחסרא והכי קתני. chasuri micheisra vehachi katani. It's like רב
פנחס Rav Pinchas משמיה דרבא. mishmeih d'Rava. דאמר רב פנחס משמיה דרבא,
De'amar Rav Pinchas mishmeih d'Rava, כל הנודרת על דעת
בעלה היא נודרת. kol hanoderes al daas baala hi noderes. This partly
explains also the התורה'ס haTorah's reason why the husband annuls it. When
a wife makes a vow, there's always like the implicit understanding, if
my husband agrees. Now it's funny, you don't—why do you need that
since anyway it's based on the husband annulling? So when we learn
נדרים Nedarim we'll worry about why you need him to give that
reason. But the point being that it's like the case of the
lamp blowing out. She always would make it, you know, with the
understanding that it might not be lasting. That if my my husband
might not like it, he might annul it, so it's never considered
to be the same degree of like fully off-limits, it's because there's
always the possibility that it'll be—that that my husband won't agree and
then it'll be permissible to me on שבת. Shabbos. So it's never
fully off-limits.
But then if he made the—right.
So now we're going to get to the case not of— the
husband annulling, but of getting some third party to void it. So
let's take a look.
We're talking מוקצה muktzeh here?
Yes, she made a vow, so there's מוקצה muktzeh not to touch
something. Not to, no, or not to eat something, let's say. Right,
so then the question also becomes how does it become מוקצה muktzeh
if it's just about eating as opposed to about moving and moving?
By the way, מוקצה, muktzeh, you're allowed to touch מוקצה, muktzeh, right?
When we grew up we said מוקצה muktzeh is sort of like
cooties, you're not allowed to touch it, but you are allowed to
touch מוקצה. muktzeh. What you can't do is moving it. So that's
תוספות's Tosafot's question. Let's finish the גמרא Gemara and then I'll go
back to that issue about like eating versus moving and so on.
Okay, so let's hold off for that a second. But now we
move on, fine. That's the case of the woman making the vow,
you could say it was always somewhat in a held it, you
know, not finalized. But how about the case of another of making
a vow and getting a third party to annul it? So the
גמרא Gemara says, תא שמע, Ta shma, how about the end of
that? נשאלין לנדרים, Nishalin l'nedarim,
you can get an annulment of a vow שלצורך שבת, shel'tzorech Shabbat,
as long as there's a שבת Shabbat purpose בשבת. b'Shabbat. And you
can do it on שבת. Shabbat. ואמאי, V'amai, how you get around
the מוקצה muktzeh issue? לימא מי יימר דמזדקק ליה חכמא, Leima mi
yeimar d'mizdakeik lei chachama, how do you know get a sage will
agree to annul your vow? Meaning maybe he'll hear it and he
won't agree to your reasonings and so on. So התם, Hatam, לא,
אי לא מזדקק ליה חכמא, lo, i lo mizdakeik lei chachama,
if you can't find a sage, סגי ליה בג' הדיוטות. sagi lei
b'gimmel hedyotot. So maybe it also meant how do you know you'll
find the חכם? chacham? But he tells look, you don't even really
need a sage there. You can just find three laypeople and they
can annul a vow. הכא מי יימר דמזדקק ליה חכם, Hacha mi
yeimar d'mizdakeik lei chacham, here by the בכור, bechor, three laypeople aren't
enough, you really need a sage and therefore you might not find
it. So again, I've been giving you תוספות's Tosafot's reason which makes
the difference even more obvious, that a sage is not allowed to
rule by a בכור. bechor. If you read the surface of the
גמרא, Gemara, it's not making that big of a difference. It's just
saying like how do you know you'll find the right person? And
it says, well, because by a normal vow, how hard is it?
Three laypeople. But by a בכור, bechor, not so obvious, and therefore
it's much more off-limits. Okay, now, the גמרא Gemara says like this,
now let's take a look before we continue on תוספות, Tosafot, which
is this issue about vows, which is very important. This question about
eating versus moving and you versus other people. So if you take
a look at
תוספות מי יימר דמזדקק ליה בעל, Tosafot Mi yeimar d'mizdakeik lei ba'al,
you see that? It's the second מי. mi. He says like this,
ואע"ג דפירש דנדרה מהם אינם מוקצים לענין טלטול. V'af al gav d'peireish
d'nadra meihem einam muktzim l'inyan tiltul. Right, there's your the first word
of תוספות. Tosafot.
The second תוספות Tosafot מי. mi. There are three מי, mi's, the
second one. Okay, ואע"ג דפירש דנדרה מהם אינם מוקצים לענין טלטול. V'af
al gav d'peireish d'nadra meihem einam muktzim l'inyan tiltul. I don't get
it, says what's the question? You're allowed to even if she can't
eat the fruit, she can move them. דהא חזו לשאר בני אדם.
D'ha chazu l'sh'ar bnei adam. Now he gives it's question if this
is the same point or a different point. Other people can actually
eat the fruit. So what's the big deal anyway? מכל מקום אית
לן למימר, Mikol makom it lan l'meimar, so first of all you
see just because I made the vow doesn't make it מוקצה muktzeh
to you. It'd be מוקצה muktzeh to me, it's not מוקצה muktzeh
to you, it's my vow, right? So that's מוקצה muktzeh to one
person, not to another. Nevertheless, אית לן למימר מיגו דאיתקצאי בין השמשות
איתקצאי לכולי יומא. it lan l'meimar migo d'itkatzai bein hashmashot itkatzai l'chulei
yoma.
Nevertheless,
maybe since I you know, even though really the only thing I
can't do is eat them, but if I'm not going to eat
fruit, what else am I going to do with them? So maybe
the fact that they're off-limits for eating makes them completely off-limits. אי
נמי, I nami, says תוספות, Tosafot, yeah, אי נמי, I nami, well,
no, for me at least, אי נמי, I nami, says תוספות, Tosafot,
מה בפירוש דנדרה ואסרתם לכל אדם. Ma b'peirush d'nadra v'asartem l'chol adam.
I actually made it forbidden on everybody. Okay, they're my fruit. But
again, תוספות's Tosafot's primary issue here is is whether they're אסור assur
to everybody or just to me. Okay, whereas you could also the
other question which is whoever they're אסור assur to, just because they're
אסור assur to eat doesn't mean that they're completely אסור. assur. תוספות's
Tosafot's bigger concern seems to be if they're not אסור assur to
other people, maybe they're not מוקצה. muktzeh. Okay, so part of what
תוספות Tosafot is dealing with is how when something is אסור assur
only to one person and not others, how מוקצה muktzeh can it
really become? Okay, so that those issues about eating versus moving, whatever,
discussed in תוספות, Tosafot, again, the resolution is not so clear, but
at least I wanted you to see that the issues were discussed.
Let's now just finish up the גמרא. Gemara. It says about does
does רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon hold that if it's off-limits בין השמשות,
bein hashmashot, it remains off-limits? So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
what time is it by the way? Oh, we're run running up.
Okay, my watch isn't working. Let's try to read one more line.
It says like this, רמי ליה אביי לרב יוסף. Rami lei Abaye
l'Rav Yosef. So אביי Abaye asked רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, מי אמר
רבי שמעון כבתה מותר לטלטלה? Mi amar Rabbi Shimon kavta mutar l'taltela?
כבתה אין לא כבתה לא. Kavta in lo kavta lo. How did
did רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon really say that so before we said
maybe sometimes it does remain forbidden if it was really completely off-limits,
like the בכור. bechor. Now we're going to ask the flip question:
why when it's burning, even when it's burning, why is that a
problem? מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, why are you not allowed to move
it when it's burning? דילמא בהדי דנקט ליה כבתה. Dilma bahadi d'nakat
lei kavta. Because you're afraid that if you move it we're assuming
what's the only reason you can't move the lamp if רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon doesn't hold of מוקצה? muktzeh? What's the only reason you
can't move it? Because as you're moving it, it'll blow out. So
he says but one minute, הא שמענא ליה לרבי שמעון דבר שאינו
מתכוין מותר. Ha shamna lei l'Rabbi Shimon davar she'eino mitkavein mutar.
But רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that if it's unintended, it's permissible.
And it won't definitely blow out. So now we're like re-questioning the
whole thing. The one thing we said רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said
was a problem was when it was burning. But why is that
a problem? Who cares? Move it. Okay, so what? It won't definitely
go out. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon doesn't have a problem with that.
דתניא, Detanya, ותני ברייתא, v'tani Baraita, רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon Omer,
גורר אדם כסא מטה וספסל, gorer adam kissei mitta v'safsal, ובלבד שלא
יתכוון לעשות חריץ. ubilvad shelo yiskayven la'asos charitz.
You can drag the bench, you know, through mud or whatever, through
dirt, as long as you're not intending to make a furrow. So
why can't you move this lamp if he generally doesn't hold of
מוקצה? muktzah? Who cares? It won't definitely go out. So the גמרא
Gemara says no. כל היכא דכי מכוון איכא איסור דאורייתא, Kol heicha
dechi michaven ika issur d'Oraisa, כי לא מכוון גזר רבי שמעון מדרבנן.
ki lo michaven gazar Rabbi Shimon mi'drabbanan.
When, had you done it intentionally, it would be a תורה Torah
violation, then he doesn't let you do it even if you're not
intending, then he doesn't allow you do it even if you're not
intending. כל היכא דכי מכוון איכא איסור דרבנן, Kol heicha dechi michaven
ika issur d'rabbanan, if at most we're dealing with a דרבנן d'rabbanan
problem, כי לא מכוון שרי רבי שמעון לכתחילה. ki lo michaven shari
Rabbi Shimon l'chatchila. Then, if you're not intending, he does allow it.
So we're going to discuss this tomorrow, but this is—the גמרא's Gemara
going to reject it, because the גמרא's Gemara going to say רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon always allows אינו מתכוון. aino miskaven. But at this
stage what the גמרא's Gemara saying is רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon doesn't
always allow אינו מתכוון. aino miskaven. He allows אינו מתכוון aino miskaven
dragging the bench through the yard, because even if you did it
intentionally, it would only be rabbinic. Why would it only be rabbinic?
That's not a normal way a person makes a furrow; that's a
שינוי. shinui. So by carrying the lamp, since if you did it
intentionally it would be biblical, there רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon actually says
I—extinguishing a lamp on שבת, Shabbos, if you actually did blow it
out, that would be biblical if you intended to extinguish it, right?
If you intended. So since if you intended it would be biblical,
he doesn't want you doing it even if you're not intending. The
only reason he allows you with the bench is because even if
you intended, it was only be rabbinic because it's not the normal
way of making a furrow. So the גמרא Gemara is going to
reject this, because we know רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon always allows אינו
מתכוון. aino miskaven. So we will resume tomorrow to have this question,
why can't you carry the lamp for רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, even
if it blows out, you're not intending and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
is not bothered with אינו מתכוון? aino miskaven? So we will pick
up with that tomorrow. Okay.